Good morning, my name is Dan Margolis, I'm filling in for Rabbi
Linzer while he's away on vacation. Today is the twenty-seventh of תמוז,
Tammuz, Tuesday morning, and we are on נדרים נ עמוד ב Nedarim
Nun Amud Bet toward the bottom, the story of the wedding of
רבי שמעון ברבי. Rabbi Shimon Be-Rabbi. We'll finish up there and then
we'll continue on נ"א. Nun Aleph. נ"א עמוד ב Nun Aleph Amud
Bet is going to go relatively quickly, so we don't have to
worry too much about the time I think. All right, so we're
starting on one, two, three, about eight lines from the bottom on
נ עמוד ב. Nun Amud Bet. רבי עבד ליה הילולא לרבי שמעון
ברבי. Rabbi avad lei hilula le-Rabbi Shimon Be-Rabbi. So רבי Rabbi made
a wedding feast for his son, רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
And as we saw from the מפרש meforesh yesterday, it was mentioned
that, and it becomes clear later in the story, that he did
not invite בר קפרא. Bar Kappara. בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, one of
the great תנאים Tannaim of the time. It seems strange that why
he didn't invite him. We're going to see a little bit more
about the relationship between רבי Rabbi and בר קפרא Bar Kappara and
perhaps that would explain why he wouldn't want him at the wedding.
So we'll see that story after this story. So this story says
here, so he was very upset. כתב אבית גננא עשרין וארבע אלפין
ריבואין דינרין נפקן אבית גננא דיין. ktav a-beit ginana esrin ve-arba alfin
ribo'in dinarin nafkan a-beit ginana dein. So he wrote over the wedding
hall, it's not clear who wrote the wedding hall, whether it was
בר קפרא Bar Kappara writing a graffiti in protest or whether it
was רבי Rabbi just proclaiming how much money he spent, but it
says he spent twenty-four million דינרין, dinarin, which is a very large
sum of money in order to make this grand wedding for his
son. רבי Rabbi was from a wealthy family. Okay, so he was
willing to make a fancy wedding for everyone. However, בר קפרא Bar
Kappara was upset that he wasn't invited. ולא זמניה לבר קפרא. ve-lo
zamneih le-Bar Kappara. Okay, he didn't invite בר קפרא. Bar Kappara. Okay,
אמר ליה אם לעוברי רצונו כך. amar lei im le-ovrei retzono kach.
If he does like this to עוברי רצונו, ovrei retzono, those who
are displeased with him, meaning really the reverse. בר קפרא Bar Kappara
is saying almost about himself, רבי Rabbi is bugging me, and if
רבי Rabbi gets this much money or he gets to spend this
much money even though he's bothering me. And again, this is a
phrase that really is used about a God's רצון. ratzon. עוברי רצונו,
ovrei retzono, those who transgress God's will and עושי רצונו, osei retzono,
those who do God's will. So here it's interesting that he's almost
using it to reference for himself. אמר ליה אם לעוברי רצונו כך.
amar lei im le-ovrei retzono kach. If for those who are bothering
him, meaning himself, בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, כך, kach, that they still
merit to have so much money and wealth and fame and everything,
לעושי רצונו על אחת כמה וכמה, le-osei retzono al achat kama ve-khama,
then those who do God's will, even more so that they, if
they are being appropriate, then they should hopefully be rewarded even more.
ועל אחת כמה וכמה. ve-al achat kama ve-khama. אזמניה. azmneih. אמר ליה
עושי רצונו בעולם הזה כך לעולם הבא על אחת כמה וכמה. amar
lei osei retzono ba-olam ha-zeh kach le-olam ha-ba al achat kama ve-khama.
But then finally he invited בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, sort of they
made up in some way and he said לעושי רצונו בעולם הזה
כך, le-osei retzono ba-olam ha-zeh kach, if people who really do God's
will in this world like this, in this world it's like this,
then even in עולם הבא olam ha-ba they should be much, much
more rewarded. So that shows a shift in his attitude toward רבי
Rabbi that at first he was very upset at רבי Rabbi and
he called רבינו הקדוש, Rabbeinu Ha-Kadosh, who's one of the great תנאים,
Tannaim, he called him עוברי רצונו, ovrei retzono, he said that he
was violating God's will and now he was able to recognize, well
once they made up, he said he was עושי רצונו. osei retzono.
But it's still interesting reason, you know, that they had this personal
feud almost and why they were, why he was critiquing him so
much.
It's a bit of a strange story. The next story is going
to give us some insight into why רבי Rabbi didn't really want
to have בר קפרא Bar Kappara around so much. It says יומא
דמחייך ביה רבי אתי פורענותא לעלמא. yoma de-michayach bei Rabbi ati pur'anuta
le-alma.
The day that רבי Rabbi would smile, then suffering would come into
the world. If we look in some of the ראשונים Rishonim here,
the answer, the reason for this is because
רבי Rabbi accepted upon himself to receive certain physical ailments and to
suffer greatly in order that the rest of the world wouldn't suffer
as much. Where do you see that? I think it's mentioned, if
I remember correctly, this is in the ר"ן. Ran.
I think it's mentioned other גמרא. gemara. It's not here on the
page. It's mentioned other
גמרא. gemara.
So there's something from, there was a drought for a number of
years and he accepted that to try to hold off the pains
of the drought. You have a note here?
It says סוף פרק יכין יעקב. sof perek Yakin Yaakov.
From the עין יעקב. Ein Yaakov. So the עין יעקב Ein Yaakov
brought it from another either from another גמרא gemara or another מדרש.
midrash. It's more recent. From across, across the גמרא. gemara. So עין
יעקב Ein Yaakov again is a compendium of different אגדתות agadetas from
ש"ס, Shas, which is edited together.
It used to be very popular. I don't know why it's not
so popular anymore. Okay, so a day that רבי Rabbi would then
smile, a day that he was enjoying himself, meant that he wasn't
suffering enough, that meant that the rest of the world then would
suffer more because he was enjoying himself. And therefore we see that
בר קפרא Bar Kappara is a bit of a jokester, a bit
of a comedian, and רבי Rabbi did not want to have בר
קפרא Bar Kappara hanging around because רבי Rabbi had accepted upon himself
this level of suffering in order to help other people. Maybe spending
240 million denarii?
Maybe that's why he
was...
maybe that's why he
said...
Is that a Christian symbol?
It's a bit surprising to us that it does seem like something
similar to a Christian idea that Jesus died and expiates the sins.
However, you see that idea throughout חז״ל, Chazal, it's not just a
Christian idea that great צדיקים tzadikim have a certain power to bring
atonement, that
when even different people who even received different personal punishment or suffering,
even if they don't necessarily deserve it, are somehow taking punishment away
from other people.
Again, it's like צדיקים tzadikim of the דור dor really. It's not
like everybody.
And the Christians would make the argument that he's also the צדיק
tzadik of the whole world, essentially pursuing this strategy.
Not that, you know,
it's a very interesting theological question. I did not do enough research
to get into the details of it, suffice to say I think
someone has written a paper or two about it, so we could
look it up online, yeah.
I'm not going to pretend to be a Christian theologian, but an
apparent difference is that in Christianity there is a single atoner who
was also God.
Right. And that's, you know, again, not for now. Let's keep going.
Okay. אמר ליה בר קפרא, Amar leh Bar Kappara, רבי Rebbe says
to בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, לא תבדחן ויהבנא לך ארבעין גריווי חטי.
La tivadchan vehavna lach arbain grivey chittey.
If you do not make me laugh, if you do not make
me happy,
then I will pay you forty measures of wheat. אמר ליה לחזי
מר דכל גריוא בעינא. Amar leh lechzei Mar dechol griva beina.
So let מר, Mar, meaning let רבי Rebbe himself, see that I
can bring whichever measure that I want. Okay? So now בר קפרא
Bar Kappara is going to try to play a practical joke almost
on רבי. Rebbe. I,
after reading this גמרא, Gemara, I still don't exactly understand what was
so strange about it, but it seems very humorous at the time.
Okay, so he says...
You had to be there to get it.
Indeed. דבעינא שקילנא. Debeina shakilna. That I want... that I want to
take. So שקל דיקולא רבה. Shakal dikula raba. He took a large
basket. חפייה כופרא. Chafyei kufra. And he coated it with pitch, with
tar of some kind. וצחפיה ארישיה. Vetzachfyei areishei. And he carried it
on his head. Okay, so he has a very large basket. Presumably,
he's going to ask for a lot of wheat. That's not... I
don't think that that's in any way funny and somehow they coated
the inside with pitch. Again, I don't really understand what's going on
with the story. ואזל ואמר ליה, Veazal veamar leh, ליתי לי מר
ארבעין גריווי חטי, Leiti li Mar arbain grivey chittey, דדרשינא בך אוחו,
dedarshina bach ocho, רבי... Rebbe... אמר ליה, Amar leh, לאו אזהרתך דלא
תבדחן? Lav azhartach dela tivadchan? אמר ליה, Amar leh, חטי דדרשינא קא
נסיבנא. Chittey dedarshina ka nasivna.
So he says: So I want to take the forty measures of
wheat that I asked for. And רבי Rebbe is basically upset, he's
like: Why are you joking around with me? Why are you making
me laugh? He says: I know, I just came to take the
wheat that you promised... that I was promised.
Because... so I don't exactly understand. He said: If you don't make
me laugh, then I'll pay you the wheat. And then he shows
up to get the wheat, but it's with this strange basket. And
somehow רבי Rebbe takes that as a joke, so he says: No,
you don't deserve the wheat. He says: No, I'm just coming to
take the wheat. So it's some kind of a play on the
fact that he's doing it in a strange way in order to
get the wheat, so he's really asking for the wheat even though
he's playing a joke even as he's doing it. I don't exactly
understand the humor in the situation. Okay.
Another translation of סחפיה sachfyei is he put it
upside down as I understand it. What? Upside down? Upside... what, so
then the tar sticks to his head?
I mean, was רבי Rebbe three years old?
What's funny?
It's not funny in any way. Maybe... oh, so that it's empty,
it's face-down so he can't fill it up with anything.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara definitely does have better jokes than this. But...
okay, we'll see now he's going to be a little bit more...
more annoying than humorous maybe, and we'll see who gets frustrated about
what. So אמר ליה בר קפרא לברתיה דרבי. Amar leh Bar Kappara
livratei deRebbe. So בר קפרא Bar Kappara said to the daughter of
רבי Rebbe and presumably this was at least somehow around the wedding
time because he's going... they're going to go to a party together.
He says: למחר שתינא חמרא בריקודי דאבוך ובקירקוני דאמך. Lemachar shatina chamra
berikuda deavuch uvekirkunei deimmach.
I will tomorrow... I will drink wine while your father is dancing
and your mother is singing or cackling. This גמרא Gemara comes to
be a question about the question of קול אשה, kol isha, because
many people wanted to say, you know, based on the גמרא Gemara
in ברכות Berachot and other sources, look we say that שמואל Shmuel
had the opinion קול באשה ערוה, kol beisha ervah, that a woman's
voice is ערוה, ervah, and here we see that בר קפרא Bar
Kappara was going to listen to רבי's Rebbe wife singing.
And the יעבץ Ya'avetz quotes this גמרא Gemara as one of his
examples of places in ש״ס Shas where the תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים
Amoraim seem to be violating הלכות halachot that are normative
for today.
Well I brought it up now! I just raised the topic. It's
an interesting topic.
No, or like you know, the line before the end of the
previous little skit. Yes, right.
אמר ליה חיפי דרישנא כנסיבנא.
Amar lei chifi
derishna kanisivna. Yeah, how do you translate that? חיפי דרישנא... Chifi derishna...
the width that I ask for now I'm going to come to
take, right.
Chana at a wedding.
I see what you mean. נסיבנא, Nasivna, right, could be a pun
on the wedding. Right, that's an also good point.
But again this is sort of seems to be sort of all
the wedding everything.
No, or maybe I mean look, you always have you have the
נשות מקוננות, Nashot Mekonnot, so we always have that, so be you
know, or maybe at the wedding it's a little different.
Right, maybe it's different. Right, that's part of the question is right
there are certain... right, so and the מפרש Meforesh trying to avoid
the question of singing, the מפרש Meforesh says that it's not anything
to do with singing, that it has to do with pouring the
wine, but the ר"ן Ran says it's singing. Okay, we keep going.
So he said this to the daughter of רבי, Rebbe, seemingly now
he's setting the stage for what he's actually going to do. So
now we're going to hear the story. So בן אלעשה חתניה דרבי
הוה.
Ben Elasa
chatneih d'Rebbe hava. So Ben Elasa who was very rich was the
son-in-law of רבי, Rebbe, so presumably this is the husband of the
same daughter who he told this to. Okay, ואושר גדול הוה, V'osher
gadol hava, he was very rich. אזמניה לבי הילולא דרבי שמעון ברבי
Azmanei l'bei hilula d'Rabbi Shimon bar Rebbe and he was also invited
to the his brother-in-law's wedding. That makes more sense than בר קפרא
Bar Kappara who seems to have been one of רבי's Rebbe not
so good friends. So the רבי's Rebbe son-in-law was at the wedding.
אמר ליה בר קפרא לרבי. Amar lei Bar Kappara l'Rebbe. So Bar
Kappara said to רבי, Rebbe, now he's going to do some different
sort of wordplay דרשות Drashot on different פסוקים Psukim about the עריות,
Arayos, some from ויקרא פרק כ Vayikra Perek Chaf and some from
ויקרא פרק יח. Vayikra Perek Yud-Chet.
Again why is this appropriate conversation for a wedding? I'm not exactly
sure.
Some try to put this in the context of the same reason
we read the פרשה Parsha of the עריות Arayos on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur afternoon, that the last משנה Mishna in מסכת תענית Masechet
Taanit says that on that the happiest occasions were יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and ט"ו באב Tu B'Av and they would go out and
do these various flirtations and things. So on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
when the people are very happy, almost you know it's a strange
vision of יום כיפור Yom Kippur people speak about this a lot,
but we need to be conscious of the עריות Arayos because people
are going out and flirting and doing things. So maybe the same
is true for a wedding, that at a wedding people are also
getting flirtatious and casual with each other. So somehow he wants to
to point out the problems of עריות Arayos or maybe he's just
trying to make some kind of awkward small talk, I'm not exactly
sure. But בר קפרא Bar Kappara says to רבי, Rebbe, מאי תועבה?
Mai To'evah? What does it mean the word תועבה To'evah in reference
to
homosexual sex?
An interesting thing to talk about at a wedding.
It's an interesting thing to talk about at a wedding, yes. This
is true. So he says...
well it refers to other things as well.
So but in this context it seems based on the other references
and again, right, תועבה To'evah is used for what eight different מצוות
Mitzvot in the תורה? Torah? At least from context because of the
other examples he brings up. He mentions what's תועבה, To'evah, what's תבל,
Tevel, and what's זמה, Zimah, that those are each examples from the
עריות Arayos there in ויקרא. Vayikra. It could be something else for
sure. But he says... well at least again from context it becomes
clear. So he says תועבה, To'evah, כל דאמר ליה רבי
דהכין הוא תועבה פרכה בר קפרא. Kol d'amar lei Rebbe d'hachin hu
To'evah parcha Bar Kappara. Everything that רבי Rebbe tried to make a
דרשה Drasha on what the word תועבה To'evah means, then בר קפרא
Bar Kappara answered them, he threw them away, he rejected them. אמר
ליה פריש את. Amar lei perish at. So he says you explain
it. אמר ליה תיתי דביתך תרמי לי
נטלא חדא רמיא ליה.
Amar lei teti
deveitach tirmey li natla chada ramya lei. So he says let your
wife bring me a cup of wine. So she brought him. אמר
ליה לרבי קום רקוד לי Amar lei l'Rebbe kum rakod li and
you רבי Rebbe you have to get up and dance for me.
So now he's sort of was setting the stage for his what
he had set up already which was that he said to the
daughter tomorrow if I'm going to pull this prank I'm going to
get רבי Rebbe to pour the wine and I'm going to...
right. Well maybe that's what people say pouring the wine.
Right, so that's why the מפרש Meforesh says pouring the wine because
in the story it seems like pouring the wine. Again, yeah, what
does the word mean? Fine, it means pouring the wine. But the
ר"ן Ran says it means singing. So I don't know and it
sounds like from the what the word means that it means singing.
Anyway, so he says fine, so you pour the wine and רבי
Rebbe קום רקוד לי, Kum rakod li, get up and dance for
me, דאמר ליה דהכי אמר רחמנא תועבה תועה אתה בה. D'amar lei
dehachi amar Rachmana To'evah to'eh ata bah. The word תועבה To'evah means
תועה אתה בה, To'eh ata bah, you are making a mistake with
it or with this. Okay, לכסא אחרינא, L'chasa achrina, for the next
cup, he you know he was drinking a bit at the wedding.
So after he had the next cup of wine אמר ליה מאי
תבל? Amar lei mai Tevel? What is the word תבל Tevel which
is used in reference to bestiality? אמר ליה כי ענינא קדמאה. Amar
lei ki anina kadma'ah. So he says like do for me again
like this. אמר ליה... amar lei sorry... so he says he answered
it like this before that he couldn't have any good answers. אמר
ליה amar lei איביד לי and he says make... do it for
me again. דאמר לך עביד de-amar lach avid so he whatever that
you said to do so he did אמר ליה amar lei תבל
הוא תבלין יש בה tevel hu tavlin yesh bah so the word
תבל tevel means rhetorically are there spices in her? Meaning is this
is this in some way enjoyable or is this in some way
more enjoyable than any other sexual act?
And that's the Torah's way of questioning the practice of bestiality. So
מי שני האי ביאה מכולהון ביאה? mi shanei hai biah mikulhon biah?
Why is this ביאה biah different from other ביאות? biot? אמר ליה
amar lei that
you would want to do it. Right.
אמר ליה amar lei ומאי זימה u-mai zimah and then he asked
further what is the word זימה? zimah? זימה zimah if I recall
correctly is אשה ובתה לא תקח ishah u-vitah lo tikach or אל
תחלל
את בתך.
al
techalel et bitcha.
Don't don't
make your daughter to go out as a prostitute. So that's what
the word זימה zimah is in reference to in the פסוק pasuk
there, sorry ולא תזנה
הארץ
ve-lo
tizneh
ha-aretz yeah ולא תזנה הארץ ומלאה הארץ זימה ve-lo tizneh ha-aretz u-malah
ha-aretz zimah that the land will be full of זימה. zimah. So
זימה zimah sounds like in some reference to
prostitution or just more promiscuous sexual activity in general. So ומאי זימה?
u-mai zimah? אמר ליה עביד כי אנינא קדמא avid ki anina kadma
עביד avid so do for me like you did before he did
it and אמר ליה זו מה היא? zo mah hi? זו מה
היא zo mah hi meaning this one who is she? Presumably the
people who would
know because the people are yeah exactly
people are sleeping around then there will be children with unknown parentage
and that's the topic of the fourth פרק perek of
קידושין. kiddushin. So לא יכיל בן אלעשה למסבל. lo yachil ben alasa
lemisbal. So בן אלעשה ben alasa couldn't handle it because he was
getting really annoyed why is בר קפרא bar kappara doing all these
strange דרשות drashot and things. Interestingly enough it doesn't say that רבי
rebbe got fed up with it. Yeah some people note that רבי
rebbe just wanted to learn תורה. torah. Here he is דרשנ-ינג darshening
פסוקים pesukim and explaining to him the words and רבי rebbe really
had this love of תורה torah and his son-in-law was maybe sort
of more more sophisticated in a way and was able to realize
that this was a joke or some kind of a strange
conversation.
A strange conversation to have at a wedding.
A strange conversation to have at a wedding but רבי rebbe was
just there trying to learn the תורה torah so he didn't get
upset but בן אלעשה ben alasa got upset. So בן אלעשה ben
alasa got upset קם ונפק kam ve-nafak he got up and he
left
הוא ואיתתיה hu ve-ittateih
he and his wife and the wife was the daughter of
רבי rebbe מתמן metaman מה בן אלעשה mah ben alasa so מתמן
metaman they left from there. Okay מה בן אלעשה mah ben alasa
so who is this בן אלעשה ben alasa meaning what what did
he do? So we're going to find out sort of what what
did he spend his money on because we said he was very
rich. So how did he spend his money? ומה בן אלעשה u-mah
ben alasa דתניא de-tanya לא
לחנם lo le-chinam
לא לחנם lo le-chinam פיזר בן אלעשה את מעותיו. pizer ben alasa
et ma'otav. He did not spread out his money for for חנם
chinam for nothingness it was actually for something very important אלא להראות
בהן תספורת של כהן גדול. ela lehar'ot bahen tisporet shel kohen gadol.
The כהן גדול kohen gadol has a חיוב chiyuv to have a
special haircut. There are three different categories of people who have to
get special haircuts. The king has a haircut every day and that's
also comes up in the discussion in יומא yoma about the fact
that יפיך תחזינה עיניך yofyecha techzenah einecha the king the king can
even wash his face on יום כיפור yom kippur because he needs
to look presentable he's the king after all. The כהן גדול kohen
gadol has to get a haircut every week in order that his
hair and it has a special haircut that's part of how the
כהן גדול kohen gadol is supposed to dress which we're going to
see in a minute what that haircut is. And the regular כהנים
kohanim have to get a haircut once a month. So בן אלעשה
ben alasa wanted to spend his money to replicate or to duplicate
the haircut of the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Remember if he's בן
אלעשה ben alasa and he's the son-in-law of רבי, rebbe, רבי rebbe
is around the year what 200 or so 180 so this is
already after the destruction of the בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. So בן
אלעשה ben alasa is in a certain sense trying to show people
what it what it was like at the time of the מקדש
mikdash in some way he's trying to emulate or replicate that experience
for people who did not get to see the כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. Still some of that messianic hope still even 130 years
later. Right in some sense that
he was anticipating that the temple would be restored relatively soon. He
was anticipating that the haircut of the כהן גדול kohen gadol would
come back. And I think it's an interesting הלכתי halachic question some
people have discussed whether nowadays
when the temple will be rebuilt however it is whether the כהן
גדול kohen gadol will have the same haircut as he had back
then or whether this is something that needs to sort of catch
up with the times. So that's an interesting question as well. So
he spent his money להראות בהן תספורת של כהן גדול lehar'ot bahen
tisporet shel kohen gadol to show off the haircut of the כהן
גדול kohen gadol דכתיב de-chtiv כסום יכסמו את ראשיהם kasom yichsemu et
rosheihem
they have to cut their hair כסום יכסמו kasom yichsemu this describes
sort of a different kind of a haircut it's trimmed in a
certain way they have to trim their hair. Okay תנא כעין לולינית
tana ke-ein lulinit
it is the לולינית lulonite לולין lulian haircut מאי לולינית? mai lulinit?
אמר רב יהודה amar rav yehuda תספורת יחידית tisporet yechidit היכי דמי
heichi dami this special haircut. sort of, how was it? אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, so, meaning, רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, one of the אמוראים,
Amoraim, was asking, I don't understand, what is this special haircut? So
רבא Rava explains: ראשו של זה בצד עיקרו של זה. rosho shel
zeh betzad ikaro shel zeh. The head of this hair is next
to the roots of the next hair.
It seems to sound like the לולב, lulav, what they say, or
the הדס, hadas, what they say, ideally to be that way.
So it seems something like this, that the hair, it seems like
almost some kind of a buzz cut, that the head of one
hair is over the roots of the next hair. It seems like
a very short haircut, which at that time would be very difficult
to secure. They didn't have the sharpest and fanciest trimmers and scissors
and things like that. So they probably had to have a very
delicate process, and that was why it was so expensive.
Like an absolute depilatory.
No, because then it would just remove the hair entirely. The whole
point of this haircut is that it's a very fancy expensive haircut.
So you have to have someone who has an iron or scissors
or something like this, it would be very expensive. So, like
some sort of cornrows. Cornrows, okay, so the רי"ף Rif says it's
more like cornrows, that's also interesting.
My interpretation of that is hilarious.
So
I don't know, you know, this is like when you're studying in
לוליאני, luliyani, לולא, lula,
is that the
לוליאני?
luliyani? לוליאני. Luliyani. לוליאני Luliyani hair.
So in Latin, that means wool.
So maybe, I don't know. That's an allusion. That's all. Fancy haircut.
בן אלעשה Ben Elasa replicated the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol haircut.
We had. Is it seen as a good way to spend your
money?
So it's not necessarily seen as a good way, it wasn't a
waste of money, it was like a strange kind of indulgence maybe.
Again, he's trying to demonstrate, you know, like the people imagine that
someone would come and, you know, build a replica of the מנורה
Menorah from the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash made of solid gold. Some
people in Israel for sure would think that that's not the best
use of that money. Some people think it is a good use
of the money. Again, some people think it's an עבירה aveira to
try to build the כלים keilim of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Okay, so that's where we are with דלעת הרמוצה. dilat haramuza. So
the משנה Mishna had said, besides the ביצה, beitza, the egg that
we saw yesterday discussing the medicinal aspect of this very hard-boiled egg.
Also interesting to note, there's a חרם cherem of the גאונים Geonim
that we shouldn't follow any of the medicines mentioned in the גמרא
Gemara since the time of the גאונים, Geonim, which was relatively recently
after the time of the גמרא. Gemara. They said you're not allowed.
You're not allowed to try to do this medicine, maybe it worked
for them, it doesn't work for us. So don't do it. Okay,
but what about this דלעת הרמוצה? dilat haramuza? So we're going to
ask. מאי דלעת הרמוצה? Mai dilat haramuza? What is this רמוצה ramuza
דלעת? dilat? דלעת Dilat usually means some kind of a gourd or
a squash or a pumpkin.
That's one of the things you could have.
So that's one of the things that you can have even if
you took a נדר neder against eating
תבשיל. tavshil. תבשיל שאיני טועם, Tavshil she'eni to'eim, you're allowed to eat
this ביצה beitza and you're allowed to eat this דלעת. dilat. So
what is this דלעת? dilat? דלעת הרמוצה, אמר שמואל, קרא
כרקוזאי.
Dilat haramuza, amar
Shmuel, kara karkuzai. It is the כרקוזאי karkuzai קרא. kara. קרא Kara
is a squash. It is a squash, yeah. So he says, דלעת
הרמוצה Dilat HaRamuza is קרא כרקוזאי. kara karkuzai. רב אשי אמר דלעת
הטמונה ברמץ. Rav Ashi amar dilat hatmuna beremetz. רב אשי Rav Ashi
says it is pumpkin which has been buried in hot coals and
it's sort of pit-roasted in the heat of the coals. Ah, so
now we have to challenge. איתיביה רבינא לרב אשי. Itvei Ravina leRav
Ashi. רבינא Ravina disproves רב אשי's Rav Ashi position.
Wait, so it can't be something cooked? It can't be something put
in?
Meaning, I cannot have תבשיל, tavshil, whatever תבשיל tavshil is, however I
would be allowed to eat this very hard-boiled type of egg and
I would be.
No, but I'm saying the gourd, the gourd isn't even cooked, it's
like roasted, you said.
Well, let's see, let's see.
You can't have anything roasted, you can't say I have anything cooked,
I can have like a barbecue, right?
In this,
so we're just, we're going to refute רב אשי's Rav Ashi position
and it's going to be a certain species of gourd, which then
again, it was going to say that the preparation method of preparation
is still relatively unknown to us as well as the details of
why this would not fall into the category of תבשיל. tavshil. But
in some way, even if it's prepared like you're saying, it should
be prepared in some way like a תבשיל, tavshil, but it's an
exception to the rule.
Wait, so the thing is,
meaning if I said I can't have anything cooked, then clearly you
can have something grilled, right?
Presumably, that was what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said.
Well then why the gourd then? I mean, it can be anything.
Okay, so that's why the ביצה beitza also. These are certain special
exceptions.
No, but ביצה beitza is boiled or whatever it is, right?
Okay, so that must be that this is also some kind of
an exception. We're going to see that רב אשי's Rav Ashi position
is refuted. If you want to work hard to figure out how
רב אשי Rav Ashi could have even said that, if it doesn't
even seem like it would fit with the לשון lashon of the
נדר, neder, we'd have to go much more בעיון be'iyun to spend
time on that. Okay, איתיביה רבינא לרב אשי. Itvei Ravina leRav Ashi.
רבינא Ravina refutes רב אשי's Rav Ashi position. רבי נחמיה אומר, Rabbi
Nechemia omer, he's quoting from מסכת כלאים, Masechet Kilayim, רבי נחמיה אומר
דלעת ארמית, Rabbi Nechemia omer dilat arammit, the Aramean pumpkin, היא דלעת
המצרית, hi dilat hamitzrit, which is the same as the Egyptian pumpkin,
כלאים עם היוונית, kilayim im hayevanit, it is כלאים kilayim if cross-bred
with the Greek pumpkins. In other words, they are close enough related
to that they can be כלאיים Kilayim without being far enough of
related that they're not כלאיים Kilayim because the prohibition on כלאיים Kilayim
only applies to a narrow range of things which are not identical
but are also not so far apart that they are incompatible. They
have to be somewhat similar. For example, cross-breeding with a donkey with
a wild type of donkeys and different things like that. And that's
I think comes up, I think it's in the first פרק Perek
of כלאיים. Kilayim. Yeah, the first פרק Perek of כלאיים. Kilayim. So
the first פרק Perek in כלאיים Kilayim goes through all those different
examples.
Best פרק Perek I've ever...
Well, because we don't know all of the species. We're not familiar
with this kind of donkey and this kind of squash and this
kind of peas, so we don't know what is it mean when
it's saying this one is related, you know, is closely related to
this one. But anyway, so the Aramean slash Egyptian type of pumpkin,
which is one species, is כלאיים Kilayim with the Greek pumpkin and
כלאיים עם הרמוצה, Kilayim im HaRemutza, and it is כלאיים Kilayim with
the רמוצה Remutza pumpkin. Proof that רמוצה Remutza pumpkin is just some
kind of pumpkin. It's not any method of preparation. It's just the
species.
Yeah, because it didn't make sense anyway, the method of preparation.
So the method of preparation example from רב אשי Rav Ashi we'll
have to look further in and say תיובתא. Tyuvta. Interesting. So that's
how we left off. It must be that רב אשי Rav Ashi
is wrong. Presumably then, if רב אשי Rav Ashi was disagreeing with
שמואל, Shmuel, so what שמואל Shmuel said, קרא כרכוזי, Kara Karkuzai, it's
the כרכוזיין Karkuzayan
squash, so that's just another type of species name and therefore, and
that's the same as רבינא's Ravina's decision. Yeah.
In
a dispute between רבינא Ravina and רב אשי, Rav Ashi, who do
we usually go by?
Who do we usually go by? רבינא Ravina and רב אשי? Rav
Ashi? I don't know if we have a rule for between רבינא
Ravina and רב אשי? Rav Ashi? I don't remember. Because we say
that רבינא Ravina and רב אשי Rav Ashi both...
I seem to recall רב
אשי Rav Ashi usually wins these arguments and here he's losing.
So here he's losing because רבינא Ravina brought him a משנה Mishna
that he didn't pay attention. And the question here, רב אשי Rav
Ashi didn't quote from the משנה. Mishna.
רב אשי Rav Ashi didn't learn ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
Well, it's not ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. It's מסכת נדרים. Masechet Nedarim. Okay, anyway.
Keep going. The next משנה. Mishna. So הנודר ממעשה קדירה, Hanoder Mimaseh
Kedeira, and this by the way is a clause from the previous
משנה, Mishna, so it's just quoted here again because we're going to
get into those גמרות Gemarot there.
But they have a משנה Mishna here.
But this right, so this משנה Mishna is a quote from the
previous משנה. Mishna.
It's very interesting.
So you're saying that it's repeated or something?
They don't usually see מתניתין. Matnitin.
Okay, yeah.
Usually it's a new משנה. Mishna. Usually it would do גופא Gufa
or something like that.
Something, it would just be the quote. So here it's just the
quote. הנודר ממעשה קדירה, Hanoder Mimaseh Kedeira, a person takes a נדר
neder from something prepared or a dish which is prepared in a
pot, אין אסור אלא ממעשה רתחתו, ein assur ela mimaseh retachto, it's
only forbidden to get something which is a really boiled up, pot-liquidy
soup of some kind. אמר קונם היורד לקדירה, Amar Konam Hayored Likdeira,
if a person says a נדר neder that I will not get
any הנאה hana'ah from something, anything which goes into a pot, יורד
לקדירה, Yored Likdeira, goes into a pot, שאני טועם, she'ani to'em, אסור
בכל הנעשה בקדירה, assur bechol hna'aseh bikdeira, then it's forbidden to get
anything that was prepared in a pot. The difference between method of
preparation and the name of the dish. מעשה קדירה Maseh Kedeira is
a type of dish. So you're only forbidden to eat something which
is boiled up in a pot in such a way. But if
you say מן היורד לקדירה, min Hayored Likdeira, then anything that you
cook in that pot counts. The difference between the type of dish
and the method of preparation. So the גמרא Gemara says תניא, Tanya,
הנודר מן היורד לקדירה, Hanoder min Hayored Likdeira, אסור ביורד לאילפס. assur
beYored L'Ilpas. If a person, so this is from the תוספתא Tosefta
here, a person took a נדר neder from היורד לקדירה, Hayored Likdeira,
whatever goes into the pot, he's also forbidden to eat anything that
goes into an אילפס. Ilpas. אילפס Ilpas is
a frying pan of some kind.
Oh, so that's what I was going to ask. In other words,
in other words, does it mean, does it mean like, look, I'm
going to be
מודר mudar from anything that goes into this pot, right? And into
this pot is going to go a stew. So these carrots that
are going into this pot, so I'm מודר, mudar, I can't eat
those carrots. Or carrots are sometimes characteristically cooked like this way
or stir-fried in the frying pan. So if I'm מודר mudar from
the carrots that are going into this stew, I can't eat a
different carrot that is going to be cooked in an אילפס. Ilpas.
I don't think it would mean that, but it does depend on,
first of all, the whole point of this פרק Perek is we're
going אחר לשון בני אדם. achar lashon bnei adam. We follow what
people are saying. So if you say, I'm not going to eat
whatever goes into a pot, that's one thing. That would include the
carrots that are always boiled and even if they're also prepared in
a frying pan because that's יורד לקדירה Yored Likdeira presumably. So we're
going to see here what the תוספתא Tosefta is saying. We didn't
finish the quote from the תוספתא.
Tosefta. Okay, but what about the carrot? In other words, could I
eat a raw carrot? If I says in other... They normally...
Of course, it didn't go into a pot.
Right. Okay, fine. So the תוספתא Tosefta says further, right?
The תוספתא Tosefta says: הנודר מן היורד לקדירה, Hanoder min Hayored Likdeira,
a person took a נדר neder not to eat whatever goes into
a pot, אסור ביורד לאילפס. assur beYored L'Ilpas. He's not allowed to
eat what
goes into the frying pan also because why?
שכבר ירד לקדירה קודם שירד לאילפס.
shekevar yarad
likdeira kodem sheyarad l'ilpas.
It
was pre-, it
was parboiled before it was prepared in the frying pan. There you
go. An ilpas. Why pot was not a small, a small aperture,
a small lip.
Okay. Like a
pan. Some kind of a pan, you know, with a cover, with
a tagine. Looks like a tagine. Okay. So, okay, מן היורד לאלפס,
min ha-yoreid la-ilpas,
if he takes a נדר neder again against eating whatever goes into
the frying pan, מותר ביורד לקדירה. mutar be-yoreid la-kedeirah.
Then he's allowed to eat whatever things which are prepared in a
pot, why? Because the preparation in the pot precedes the preparation in
the frying pan. So, but if you take a נדר neder against
whatever is prepared in the pot, then even things which are then
later
fried on the outside in order to crisp them up would be
forbidden. But if you say only about the frying pan things, then
things which were only boiled would still be permitted.
The תוספתא Tosefta continues: מן הנעשה בקדירה, min ha-na'aseh ba-kedeirah, if you
take a נדר neder from whatever is prepared in a pot, מותר
בנעשה באלפס, mutar be-na'aseh ba-ilpas, of course it's permitted to eat whatever
then is prepared in a frying pan because that's the later stage
of preparation. מן הנעשה באלפס, min ha-na'aseh ba-ilpas, מותר בנעשה בקדירה, mutar
be-na'aseh ba-kedeirah, and if you take a נדר neder against whatever's prepared
in frying pan and you're permitted to eat whatever's prepared in the
pot because neither of those is exclusive. So if you then bring
it and cook it in somewhere else, then it would be fine
because again, it's about the method of preparation.
הנודר מן היורד לתנור, ha-nodeir min ha-yoreid la-tanur, a person who takes
a נדר neder about whatever goes into an oven, אין אסור אלא
בפת. ein asur ela be-pat. The only thing which is forbidden is
bread. Now we know what kind of תנור tanur they used to
have was some kind of a conical or cylindrical oven, some kind
of like a tandoor oven, and they would stick the bread to
the side. We know from פסחים Pesachim that they also used the
oven for and from the beginning of שבת Shabbat that they also
used the oven for roasting meat.
But for the most part the עיקר ikar of the oven, the
whole point of an oven is to bake bread. The fact that
you would stick a spit of meat in the oven is sort
of, well while I have the oven going, baking my bread, I
may as well use the same fire, the same heat for this
other thing.
They didn't have baked chicken so often.
Maybe they did, but it wasn't in their minds. If a person
says whatever goes יורד לתנור, yoreid la-tanur, יורד לתנור yoreid la-tanur means
bread. That's the thing that you put into the oven. Okay. ואם
אמר כל מעשה תנור עלי, ve-im amar kol ma'aseh tanur alai, if
he says everything prepared in an oven is forbidden to me, אסור
בכל הנעשים בתנור. asur be-kol ha-na'asim ba-tanur. Then it applies to everything
prepared in an oven. Meaning the whole point of the oven is
to prepare bread, but there are other things which can be prepared
in an oven as well.
Interestingly enough, the ר"ן Ran tries to say,
okay, not the ר"ן, Ran, fine. Oh, so the other thing to
note is that the word נעשה na'aseh here sounds like it means
the final touches of the cooking. When you say נעשה בקדירה na'aseh
ba-kedeirah or נעשה באלפס, na'aseh ba-ilpas, נעשה באלפס na'aseh ba-ilpas was pre-boiled
in the קדירה kedeirah but it was finished in a pan. Okay.
Now we start the next עמוד amud נ"א עמוד ב' nun-alef amud
bet right at the top and we'll do these two משניות mishnayot
with their little bits of גמרא Gemara and then we'll be done
for the day. We'll finish on the third wide line at the
third from the bottom line. Okay. המשנה Ha-mishnah says: מן הכבוש, min
ha-kavush, if a person takes a נדר neder against כבוש, kavush, כבוש
kavush means pickled, אין אסור אלא מן הכבוש של ירק. ein asur
ela min ha-kavush shel yerak.
Okay.
So a person says, "I take a נדר neder not to taste
the pickles." Again, the word the ה', hei, ה' הידיעה, hei ha-yedi'ah,
הכבוש, ha-kavush, the pickles. The ר"ן Ran notes that that's the reason
why it only applies to vegetables. If you say "I נודר nodeir
מן כבוש" min kavush from pickled things, that would be more inclusive.
But because he said הכבוש, ha-kavush, it's the thing that people normally
pickle, which is vegetables.
Perhaps you would only say cucumbers. People also make pickled green tomatoes,
people also make pickled
this... if I would say "pickles," I mean pickled cucumbers. But if
I were in certain communities where people are making radish pickles and
this and that and kimchi and all those sorts of things, it
may be more ambiguous. And then we'd have to say
סתם נדרים להחמיר, stam nedarim le-hachmir, but פירושן להקל. peirushan le-hakel. So
then you'd have to ask the person, "Well, what did you mean
when you said pickles?" and we could then clarify. Okay.
And exactly, corned beef is a pickled beef. So that's and that's
part of what we're talking about here now. We're going to talk
about cured meats and different things like that, cured fish. So person
says כבוש שאיני טועם, kavush she-eini to'eim, the person says "I take
a נדר neder not to taste any
pickled
thing," אסור בכל הכבושים, asur be-kol ha-kevu'shim, then it's forbidden to taste
any pickles. מן השלוק, min ha-sheluk, what about stewed
or... exactly know what שלוק *shaluk* means, some kind of braised perhaps,
a method of preparing meat usually. So if a person says מן
השלוק *Min hashaluk* from the braised thing, אינו אסור אלא מן השלוק
של בשר *eino asur ela min hashaluk shel basar*. It refers specifically
to to red meat prepared in this manner. שלוק שאיני טועם *Shaluk
she-eini to-em*, but if a person says stewed or braised I will
not taste, אסור בכל השלוקים *asur bekhol hashalukim*, then it applies to
every type of braised food, whether it's meat or chicken or fish
or vegetables or anything. The גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר ליה רב אחא
בריה דרב אויא לרב אשי *Amar lei Rav Akha bereih de-Rav Avya
le-Rav Ashi*. So רב אחא בריה דרב אויא *Rav Akha bereih de-Rav
Avya* says to רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, אמר דכביש מאי דשליק מאי
דצלי מאי דמליח מאי *amar dikh-vish mai, deshalik mai, detzali mai, demaliakh
mai*. So he says, not הכבוש *hakabush* or השלוק *hashaluk* or just
with no article, no prefix, just כבוש *kabush* or שלוק *shaluk*, but
he says דכביש *dikh-vish* or דשליק *deshalik*, the thing that was prepared
in this manner, that was pickled, that was boiled, that was roasted,
that was salted, מאי *mai*? היכא משמע *hekha mashma*? What does that
mean? תיבעי tiba'ei. *tibaye*, I don't know, תיבעי *tibaye* is we said
לשון נדרים משונה *lashon nedarim meshuna*, that's the way of saying תיקו
teiku, *Teiku*. He asks a good question, we don't really know. So
because ד *de*, that was prepared in this way, does that mean
specifically the thing that's normally prepared in this way or does that
mean
anything prepared in this manner? Okay. The next משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. מן
הצלי *Min hatzali*, אינו אסור אלא מן הצלי של בשר *eino asur
ela min hatzali shel basar*. If a person takes a נדר *neder*
of the same לשון *lashon*, נדר נודר אני מן הצלי *neder noder
ani min hatzali*, a person says I take a נדר *neder* not
to get, to eat roasted meat or, to eat the roasted, the
roasted, it only applies to roasted red meat, beef of some kind,
beef or perhaps lamb as well, בשר *basar*, red meat. דברי רבי
יהודה *Divrei Rabbi Yehuda*, so רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says. צלי שאיני
טועם *Tzali she-eini to-em*, but what about a person says again roasted
I will not taste, אסור בכל הצלויים *asur bekhol hatzluyim*, then it
applies even to anything roasted. Interest- interesting why it's דברי רבי יהודה
*Divrei Rabbi Yehuda*, that the first two clauses about כבוש *kabush* and
שלוק *shaluk* were anonymous and the one about צלי *tzali* is attributed
to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, strangely perhaps there's some מחלוקת *makh-loket* about
it somewhere else, so I didn't see anything about that. Okay. מן
המליח *Min hamaliakh*, what about something salted, the salted one? And we-
we know from other contexts whenever they say מליח *maliakh* they really
mean מליח *maliakh* fish, as we're going to see. So אינו אסור
אלא מן המליח של דג dag, *eino asur ela min hamaliakh shel
dag*, it only applies to salted
fish, salt-cured fish, perhaps something more like salt cod, something dry and
hard, I don't know exactly or maybe it's more pickled. מליח *Maliakh*
sounds like something different from כבוש *kabush*, so כבוש *kabush* is prepared
in a brine, מליח *maliakh* may be a dried hard hard-dried salted.
Okay.
And you
have to soak it with water and change the water, that's perhaps
why it's considered in some cases to be dangerous to your health
at certain times of year and different things like that because it
has too much salt and it needs to be prepared a certain
way. Okay. So מן המליח של דג dag, *min hamaliakh shel dag*.
מליח שאיני טועם *Maliakh she-eini to-em*, but salted- salted I will not
taste, אסור בכל המלוחים *asur bekhol hamlukhim*, then it applies to anything
salted. Ah דג dag *dag* or דגים *dagim*. What if a person
tries to make a נדר *neder* about the word דג dag *dag*
or the word דגים *dagim* שאיני טועם *she-eini to-em*, I will not
taste. אסור בהן *Asur bahen*, then it's forbidden to them, meaning fish,
בין גדולים בין קטנים בין מלוחים בין טפלים בין חיים בין מבושלים
*bein gedolim bein ktanim bein melukhim bein tfelim bein khayim bein mevushalim*.
So then it applies to any kinds of fish, whether salted or
fresh or raw or cooked. The status of raw fish is very
interesting, obviously sushi has become very popular in recent years but it
was not in previous years. And I think many of the major
כשרות *kashrut* agencies and פוסקים *poskim* have debated the how does the
status of בישול עכו"ם *bishul akum*, the prohibition on eating food prepared
by non-Jews, a rabbinic גזירה *gzeira*, how does that apply to sushi?
Because it's eaten raw anyway, perhaps since the גזירה *gzeira* doesn't apply
to foods that are normally eaten raw, and now fish has become
something that is normally eaten
raw. Yeah.
Star-K website actually says that.
So and if Star-K then that's probably רב היינמן *Rav Heinemann's* פסק
*psak*, I don't know all the other פוסקים *poskim*, I think some.
It wasn't written by רב היינמן *Rav
Heinemann* but it was written by someone for Star-K. So I don't
know all the details but I know that it's a matter of
debate. Also note that much of sushi contains rice as well, and
rice the status of rice according to בישול עכו"ם *bishul akum* is
also complicated. So but here we have the משנה *Mishnah* talking about
sushi. So if you would say I'm not going to taste fish,
that includes sushi, it includes fresh, it includes all different kinds of
fish. Okay. And it includes small fish and large fish because the
question of the word דגים *dagim*, דגים שאיני טועם *dagim she-eini to-em*,
I'm not going to taste fish. Okay. ומותר בטרייתא טרופה ובציר *Umutar
bit-rayta trufa u-vetzir*, but it is permitted to eat the minced chopped
type fish that has the brine. I don't know exactly, it's something
like chopped herring perhaps. If someone else has a better description of
what that dish is you can feel free to share, but we'll
keep going with the משנה *mishna*. הנודר מן הצחנה hanoder min hatzachana.
אסור בטריא טרופה *hanodeir min hatziyana assur betirya trufa*, a person who
takes a נדר *neder* from צחנה tzachana, *tzachana*, צחנה tzachana? *tzachana* again
sounds like one of these prepared pickled fish dishes, the character of
which I'm not a hundred percent sure, but then he is also
prohibited בטריא טרופה *betirya trufa*, the chopped up fish, ומותר בציר ובמורייס
*umuttar betzir uvemuryas*, but is permitted with the brine of the fish
which is the juice that kind of squeezes out of the fish
and the מורייס *muryas* which is some other kind of brine that
that was included. The details of which kinds of brine were used
for which, again there are סוגיות *sugyot* in ברכות *brachot* and other
places what ציר *tzir*. I think ציר *tzir* is really the juice
that comes out of the flesh itself and מורייס *muryas* is the
brine that you prepare to pickle something else in.
Thanks says מורייס *muryas* is a Latin word.
Well that's very good, what does it mean? Fish brine, there you
go. The גמרא *gemara* in יומא *yoma*, I believe if I remember
correctly, discusses whether or not if a person consumes ציר *tzir* on
יום כיפור *yom kippur*, whether that would really stand as a violation
of the prohibition on eating or not because not really edible on
its own, only when it's prepared with the fish in some way,
but the ציר *tzir* itself may not really be eating. Okay so
that's the משנה *mishna* about these different kinds of pickled fish and
things. תניא *tanya*, we have a ברייתא *braita*. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר דג dag שאני טועם אסור בגדולים *rabbi shimon ben elazar omeir
dag she'eini to'eim assur bagedolim*, if a person says I will not
taste fish, דג *dag*, the single masculine fish, he is prohibited to
eat large fish ומותר בקטנים *umuttar baktananim*. He's permitted to eat small
fish because דג *dag*, the word דג *dag* only means large fish.
דגה dagah, שאני טועם *daga she'eini to'eim*, but דגה dagah *daga* seemingly
the feminine or diminutive form of the word for fish שאני טועם
*she'eini to'eim*, I will not taste, אסור בקטנים *assur baktananim*, it's prohibited
to eat small fish ומותר בגדולים *umuttar bagedolim*. Then he's permitted to
eat.
In our משנה
*mishna* it's דג דגים *dag dagim*. Ah, so that's why the משנה
*mishna* has seemingly some issue with the word דג *dag* or דגים
*dagim*. So this רבי שמעון בן אלעזר's *rabbi shimon ben elazar's* position
is that דג *dag* refers to large fish and דגה dagah *daga*
refers to small fish. We're going to see just in a minute
the question of what happened to יונה Yonah *yona*. We remember יונה
Yonah *yona* was swallowed by a דג *dag*, but later in the
story the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* calls the same fish a דגה dagah
*daga*. So we'll see that in a second.
Well I thought I thought it was Jonah he didn't eat the
fish the fish ate him.
Oh well well
what would happen if יונה *yona* had taken a נדר *neder* against
fish right?
Okay so that's against a יונה *yona* from a fish.
Exactly.
Well then it was יונה *yona*.
Okay so we say here, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר דג שאני
טועם אסור בגדולים ומותר בקטנים דגה dagah שאני טועם אסור בקטנים ומותר
בגדולים *rabbi shimon ben elazar omeir dag she'eini to'eim assur bagedolim umuttar
baktananim daga she'eini to'eim assur baktananim umuttar bagedolim*. דג דגה dagah שאני
טועם *dag daga she'eini to'eim*, so if he says דג דגה שאני
טועם *dag daga she'eini to'eim* that I'm not going to taste, אסור
בין בגדולים בין בקטנים *assur bein bagedolim bein baktananim*, because he said
דג דגה *dag daga*, fish fish meaning both kinds of fish together,
then it applies to both the large fish and the small fish.
אמר ליה רב פפא Rav Pappa לאביי *amar lei rav pappa le'abbaye*,
so רב פפא Rav Pappa *rav pappa* now is asking אביי Abaye,
*abbaye*, ממאי דדג שאני טועם גדול הוא *mima'i dedag she'eini to'eim gadol
hu*, how do we know that the word דג *dag* in the
masculine form refers to a large fish? דכתיב וימן ה' דג גדול
dag gadol. לבלוע את יונה *dichtiv vayman hashem dag gadol livloa et
yona* because God prepared a large fish to swallow יונה *yona* and
therefore that means it was a large fish, והא כתיב ויתפלל יונה
אל ה' אלוהיו ממעי הדגה *veha dichtiv vayitpalleil yona el hashem elohav
mimi'ei hadaga*. יונה *yona* cried out and prayed to God from the
bowels of the organs intestines of the fish that it said דגה
*daga*.
So why did he pray?
It must be that it got smaller and that's at the point
because when יונה *yona* was initially in
a big fish for three
days, he was in there for three days and he didn't דאוון
*davven*. So he was there for three days, finally when God shrank
the size of the fish and it became very claustrophobic, then יונה
*yona* felt the need to pray because it was עת צרה *eit
tzara*, it became a pressured situation. Alternatively I think this is from
another
there's oh the מהרש"א *maharsha* explains slightly differently, the מהרש"א *maharsha* says
why is the difference between דג דגה *dag daga*, why was it
דגה *daga* became more cramped? It was a God switched the fish
from a male fish to a female fish and the female fish
was full of eggs and with all of the eggs there it
was more cramped and that was why יונה *yona* felt the need
to pray. So either way it's something to think about on יום
כיפור *yom kippur* at מנחה *mincha* time that we're really coming to
God from a place of constriction and and pressure the way יונה
*yona* felt it in the in the fish.
It's still a pretty large fish if Jonah's inside it.
Well if he's inside but you can imagine I mean still it's
a large of a large fish with you know imagine the fish's
stomach right? I mean you can have you can have יונה *yona*
who's you know if יונה *yona* is sitting here right like he
could be totally swallowed in the fish like this or it could
be a much you know whatever it is from Pinocchio where the
whale is so big he can swallow it easily you know
you could accept the multidimensional fish.
Well that's another possibility. The other question of course is whether this
was a whale meaning the פסוק *pasuk* says fish we know that
whales are not fish they're mammals they have whiskers they make happy
noises. Right so everyone used to call a fish a fish so
they thought that this so maybe or it was a shark I
don't know sharks don't have such large stomachs. Neither do whales really,
especially the largest whales. The largest whales have very small stomachs because
they only eat tiny krill and plankton, so they strain out all
the water and this tiny amount of food goes down. They don't
have a big stomach, so it's a good question.
According to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the largest fish in
the ocean is the Rhincodon typus or whale shark, 12 meters long,
weighing up to 20 metric tons.
But that's only kind of because that's a fish because they're not
counting whales. Probably חזל would count a whale as a fish. That's
what I would have to guess. I'm not sure.
Also, this is about a דג גדול.
Okay, so you say, meaning רב פפא Rav Pappa asked אביי, Abaye
I don't understand their proof, and so אביי Abaye answers. אביי Abaye,
answers, oh, it seems clear from the פסוקים pesukim in יונה that
at first it was a larger fish, and that was the word
דג, and then somehow it got smaller and it was the word
דגה, became smaller. Okay, הא קשיא, ha kashya, so it's not a
challenging to my position, meaning רב פפא's really trying to say maybe
it shouldn't fit like that, so he says it's not problematic. דילמא
פלטיה דג גדול ובלעיה דג קטן. dilma paltei dag gadol uvalei dag
katan. No, I could explain the פסוקים pesukim totally differently. First יונה
was swallowed up by a large fish, then the large fish threw
him up underwater, and then a small fish came along and swallowed
him again. Now there's two fish. Now this is sort of an
Occam's razor kind of situation. Why do you have to propose two
fish where the פסוק only told you there's one
fish?
So, being in a דג, like being underwater, being,
whatever, he was immediately swallowed again by the next fish, you know,
it could be, if God can make one large fish to swallow
him, I don't see why it couldn't be a second fish. Okay,
so that's part of the question. In other words, רב פפא is
just saying to אביי, your proof that it's somehow the same fish
changed in size
and that's what the words mean is not necessarily a good
proof. אלא והדגה אשר ביאר מתה. ella veha dagah asher bayeor meta.
So the fish that were in the יאור, yeor, the Nile river
during the plague of blood died. The fish died. Ah, and which
kind of fish live in a river anyway? Must be
small
fish. קטנים מיתו גדולים לא מיתו? katanim meitu gedolim lo meitu? If
the river would turn to blood, would only the small fish die
and not the large fish? Because he said דגה means small fish
and דג means large fish, and therefore it would seem that according
to that, if we read it very precisely, that the word דגה
is used to refer to the fish in the plague of blood,
מכת דם, makat dam, then only the small fish would have died.
Correct. אלא דגה משמע גדולים ומשמע קטנים. ella dagah mashma gedolim umashma
katanim. No, דגה means
משמע גדולים, mashma gedolim, means the large fish, ומשמע קטנים, umashma katanim,
and it means the small fish as well. דגה is all-inclusive, every
kind of fish. דג still could refer to large fish. ובנדרים הלך
אחר לשון בני אדם. uvinedarim halacha achar lashon bnei adam. However, who
cares what the word means in תנך? Tanach? We already saw the
opinion, even the opinion that we thought held that we should care
about what the word means in תנך, Tanach, was eventually shown to
mean that he even holds לשון בני אדם. lashon bnei adam. It's
לכולי עלמא lekulei alma בנדרים הלך אחר לשון בני אדם. binedarim halacha
achar lashon bnei adam. We follow לשון בני אדם, lashon bnei adam,
and therefore if people are using the word דגה to mean small
fish and דג to mean large fish, then that's what we do.
We don't really care what the proof from the פסוקים pesukim is
either way. הנודר מן הצחנה. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei
Ravina lerav Ashi, אמר הרי עלי ציחין מאי? amar harei alai tzichin
mai? A person, so if a person said I will not get
any הנאה hana'ah from צחנה, so can he have ציחין? tzichin? תיבעי.
I don't know.
Maybe ציחין tzichin is the singular of צחנה?
Good question. תיקו, leave it there. So we'll pick up tomorrow right
at the bottom with the next משנה and Rabbi Linzer will most
likely be back at the end of the week. ניני. nini.